Alexander Graham Bell Family
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Article and Book File, 1901-1904, n.d. (Box 395-398)
  - Articles (Box 395)
    - "Aurora Borealis of August 21"
    - Autobiographical writings
    - "Auto-Education Continued in the Primary School" (Box 396)
    - "Condensing Water from Perspiration and from the Evaporation from Damp Clothes"
    - "Condensing Water from the Breath"
    - "Consequences of Denying Action at a Distance"
    - "Conservation of Energy"
    - "Deafness in White Cats"
    - "Discovery and Invention"
    - "The Evolution of Civilization"
    - "Experiments in Ventilating and Heating Houses"
    - "Experiments relating to Binaural Audition"
    - "Experiments with Celluloid"
    - "Extinct Reptiles Found in Nodules"
    - "A Few Notes of Progress in the Construction of an Aerodrome with an Historical Introduction"
    - "A Few Thoughts Concerning Eugenics"
    - "Fluids in Motion"
    - "The Flying Machine of the Future, as Conceived in 1892"
    - "French Pronunciation in the Melville Bell Symbols"
    - "Giving Eyes to the Ears of the Blind"
    - "The Growth of the Oral Method in America"
    - "Growth of the Oral Method of Instructing the Deaf"
    - "Is Race Suicide Possible?"
    - "Kith and Kin"
    - Letters to editors
      - Association Review
      - Daily Eastern Argus, (3 folders)
      - Lancet
      - Nature, (2 folders)
      - New York Tribune (Box 397)
      - Science, (2 folders)
    - "Making a Talking Machine"
    - "Marriages of Deaf Mutes"
    - "The Method of Instruction Pursued with Helen Keller, A Valuable Study for Teachers of the Deaf"
    - "The Multiple Telegraph"
    - "The Mystic Oral School"
    - "Natural Selection"
    - "Neighboring Worlds"
    - "Notes on Science and Progress"
    - "Observation: Twin Brother to Invention"
    - "On Anti-Trust Legislation"
    - "On Panoramas"
    - "On the Possibility of Seeing by Electricity"
    - "On Reading as a Means of Teaching Language to the Deaf"
    - "Parents' Co-Operative Association for the Support of Children"
    - "The Peace Negotiations," by Robert Lansing, comments by Alexander Graham Bell
    - "The Photophone and Conversion of Radiant Energy"
    - "Preventing Collisions with Icebergs in a Fog"
    - "The Proportion of Deaf Persons Married to Deaf Partners and to Hearing Partners"
    - "The Question of Sign Language and the Utility of Signs"
    - "Results of Collision with Stationary Particle"
    - "Saving the Six-Nippled Breed"
    - "Science and Food Supply"
    - "Science of Speech"
    - "The Scientific Education of Children"
    - "Sheep Breeding Experiments on Beinn Bhreagh"
    - "Simple Experiments"
    - "Simple Experiments: Experiments with a Floating Candle"
    - "Sound Lantern for the Blind"
    - "Studies of the Deaf"
    - "Suggested Remedy for Certain Kinds of Neurologic Pains"
    - "The Tetrahedral Principle in Kite Structure"
    - "Thoughts"
    - "Upon a Method of Teaching Language to a Very Young Congenitally Deaf Child
    - "Upon the Advancement of Visible Speech" (Box 398)
    - "Utility of Action and Gesture"
    - "Ventilation and Heating of Houses"
    - "Visible Speech as a Means of Communicating Articulation to Deaf Mutes"
    - "Warming and Cooling by Radiation"
    - "Water, Water Everywhere and Not a Drop to Drink"
    - "Weather Forecasts"
    - "What to Do with the House of Lords"
    - "When Does a Profit Become Usury?"
    - "Why Does a Cream Pitcher Have a Projecting Lip?" re Orville Wright's plane accident
    - Bound articles, 1901-1904, copies of dictations made by Charles R. Cox, Beinn Bhreagh, Nova Scotia, 1907
  - Books
    - Marriages of the Deaf in America, printed copy
    - The Mechanism of Speech, clipping and excerpt
- Speeches and Interviews File, 1876-1922, n.d. (Box 398-404)
  Speeches and handwritten and typewritten drafts and printed copies of interviews.
  Grouped by type of material. The interviews are arranged chronologically, and the speeches are arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled speeches are arranged chronologically.
  - Interviews (Box 398)
    - 1885, Nov. 7
    - 1893, June
    - 1896, Mar. 1
    - 1896, Mar. 5
    - 1901, Aug. 13 (Box 399)
    - 1910, Aug. 16
    - 1915, June 6
    - 1915, Oct. 17
    - 1916, Jan. 22
    - 1916, Mar. 14
    - 1921, June
    - 1922, Feb. 4
  - Speeches
    - "Aerial Locomotion," 13 Dec. 1906
    - "Aerial Locomotion," 7 May 1909
    - "Are There Other Worlds Than Ours"
    - "Articulation for Deaf Mutes"
    - "Conditions Affecting the Fertility of Sheep and the Sex of Their Offspring"
    - "The Connection between Sound and Electricity"
    - "Conquest of the Air"
    - "Deaf Classes in Connection with the Public Schools"
    - "Early Telephony"
    - Edison Gold Medal, presentation of
    - "Education of the Deaf"
    - "Experiments relating to Binaural Audition"
    - "A Few Thoughts Concerning Eugenics" (Box 400)
    - "Flying Machines without Wings"
    - "Formation of a Deaf-Mute Variety of the Human Race"
    - "The Growth of the Oral Method in America"
    - "The Growth of the Oral Method of Instructing the Deaf"
    - "Gulliver's Adventures among the Fluvinns"
    - "Half-Hour Evening Talks on Various Subjects," 1888-1893
    - "Heredity and Marriage"
    - "The Inheritance of Deafness"
    - "Intelligibility More Important than Absolute Accuracy in Lip Reading"
    - "Mechanism of Breathing"
    - Mechanism of speech, a series of lectures
    - "Memoir upon the Formation of a Deaf Variety of the Human Race" (Box 401)
    - "Methods of Producing Naturalness in the Speech of the Deaf"
    - "Modification of Wheatstone's Microphone and Its Applicability to Radiophone Researches"
    - "Multi-Nippled Sheep of Beinn Bhreagh"
    - "Mystic Oral School"
    - "Notes on the Development of Telephone Service"
    - "On the Notation of Kinship"
    - "On the Production of Sound by Light"
    - "A Philanthropist of the Last Century Identified as a Man"
    - "Pre-Commercial Period of the Telephone"
    - "Prehistoric Telephone Days"
    - "Preparedness for National Defense"
    - "Prizes for the Inventor"
    - "Problems Awaiting Solution"
    - "Radiophony," American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1881
    - "Radiophony," Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y., 1890
    - "Recent Developments in the Science of Aviation"
    - "Researches in Electric Telephony"
    - "Researches in Telephony"
    - "Science of Speech" (Box 402)
    - "Scientific Education of Children"
    - "Sensation and Inference"
    - "Some Seeming Impossibilities"
    - "Some Thoughts Concerning the Effects of Atmospheric Pressure upon Aeroplanes"
    - "Spectrophone"
    - "Speech"
    - Speech training, New York State Teachers' Association
    - Statistics of articulation work in America
    - Telephone
      - Addresses
        - 1876, Oct., Boston, Mass.
        - 1877
          - Jan., Washington, D.C.
          - Feb., Essex Institute, Salem, Mass.
          - Apr.-May, Boston, Mass., series
          - May
            - Lawrence, Mass.
            - New York, N.Y., series
            - Springfield, Mass.
          - Aug. 21, British Association for the Advancement of Science, Plymouth, England
          - Sept., Philosophical and Microscopical Societies, Aberdeen, Scotland (Box 403)
          - Oct. 25, Bradford, England
          - Oct., Birmingham, England
          - Nov.
            - Glasgow, Scotland
            - Greenock, Scotland
          - Nov.-Dec., London, England, series
          - Dec. 1, London, England
          - Dec., London, England
          - Undated
            - Newcastle, England
            - Providence, R.I.
      - Lectures
        - 1876-1877
        - 1917
    - "Upon an Apparatus for Determining without Pain to the Position of a Projectile of Lead or Other Metal in the Human Body"
    - "Upon Marriage"
    - "Upon the Condition of Articulation Teaching in American Schools for the Deaf"
    - "Upon the Education of the Sense of Hearing in the Value of Reading for the Deaf"
    - Visible speech
      - 1874
        - Apr., Boston Society of Arts, Boston, Mass.
        - Nov. 4, Boston Institute of Technology, Boston, Mass.
      - 1875, Nov. 1, Salem, Mass.
      - 1877, Glasgow, Scotland
      - 1880, London, England
      - 1892, American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf
      - "Visualization of Vibrations of Speech"
      - "Vowel Elements to Be Emphasized in Speech Teaching"
      - "Vowel Theories"
      - "Wireless Telegraphy"
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1878
        - Mar. 12, London, England
        - Mar., London, England
        - Oct., Hull Literary and Philosophical Society
        - Dec. 11, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Boston, Mass.
      - 1886, Oct. 23, Philosophical Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
      - 1890, Feb., Literary Society of Washington, Washington, D.C.
      - 1891, Apr. 10, Patent Congress
      - 1893, World Congress on Statistics of the Deaf, Chicago, Ill.
      - 1894, July, American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf, Chautauqua, N.Y. (Box 404)
      - 1896
        - Mar. 12, Normal School, Milwaukee, Wis.
        - July 2, American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf
        - Nov. 18, Tokyo, Japan
      - 1899
        - American Association to Promote the Teaching of Speech to the Deaf, Philadelphia, Pa.
        - Sydney, Australia
      - 1900, Oct., National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C.
      - 1915, July 28, Baddeck, Nova Scotia
      - 1916
        - Jan. 18, Aero Club of America, New York, N.Y.
        - Apr. 29, Southern Preparedness Conference, Charleston, S.C.
      - 1918
        - Jan. 12, Canadian Club, St. Catharines, Ont.
        - Apr. 15, Milwaukee City Club, Milwaukee, Wis.
        - Dec. 3, Canadian Club, Nova Scotia, Canada
      - Statement, 28 July 1915
      - List of speeches
      - Index to speeches and articles
- Miscellany, 1865-1974 (Box 404-414)
  Address books, bills and receipts, printed matter, and other miscellaneous items.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Address books, (3 folders) (Box 404)
  - Articles by persons other than Alexander Graham Bell, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 405)
  - Autographs of Alexander Graham Bell
  - Bills and receipts
  - Cancelled checks
    - 1879
    - 1881-1884, (4 folders) (Box 406)
    - 1884-1889, (3 folders) (Box 407)
    - 1890-1898, (4 folders) (Box 408)
    - 1899-1905, (5 folders) (Box 409)
    - 1906-1918, (5 folders) (Box 410)
  - Class notes (Box 411)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1969
  - Dickens, Charles, A Christmas Carol, marked by Alexander Graham Bell for reading to family at Christmas (2 copies)
  - Engagement book
  - Financial papers
  - Household expenses
  - Lesage, [?], extracts from the writings of
  - Miscellany (Box 412)
    - Fragments, lists, drawings, and unidentified material, (4 folders)
    - Note re dynamometer
    - Notebooks, (2 folders)
    - Poetry, (2 folders)
    - Quotations of Alexander Graham Bell
    - Sea charts (Box 413)
    - Travel, papers relating to
    - Writings and copies of correspondence, (1 vol.)
  - Printed matter, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 414)
- Additions, 1847-1954, n.d. (Box 414-446)
  Correspondence, data sheets, card files, printed matter, and photographs relating to the Genealogical Record Office, docket books listing applications for American and British patents, and bound volumes of the American Annals of the Deaf.
  The papers are grouped by addition and arranged alphabetically by type of material thereunder.
  - Addition I (Box 414)
    - Genealogical Record Office, Washington, D.C.
      - Age fallacy
      - Age mistakes
      - Aged people
      - Biographical data See also Container 226, same heading, and Containers 242-263, Statistical data
        - Ab-Bar, (4 folders)
        - Bar-Bra, (5 folders) (Box 415)
        - Bra-Cle, (5 folders) (Box 416)
        - Cle-Dal, (4 folders) (Box 417)
        - Dam-Fam, (5 folders) (Box 418)
        - Fam-Gif, (5 folders) (Box 419)
        - Gif-Haw, (5 folders) (Box 420)
        - Haw-Hun, (4 folders) (Box 421)
        - Hun-Law, (5 folders) (Box 422)
        - Law-McW, (5 folders) (Box 423)
        - McW-Mos, (5 folders) (Box 424)
        - Mos-Pot, (6 folders) (Box 425)
        - Pot-Rot, (5 folders) (Box 426)
        - Rou-Smi, (5 folders) (Box 427)
        - Smi-Sun, (4 folders) (Box 428)
        - Sun-Van, (5 folders) (Box 429)
        - Van-Wic, (5 folders) (Box 430)
        - Wic-Zwe, (4 folders) (Box 431)
      - Census, 1916
      - Clippings
      - Correspondence, 1915-1916 (Box 432)
      - Expenses, 1916
      - Genealogical forms
      - Genuine centenarians
      - Miscellany
      - Photograph catalog
      - Reports, 1915-1916, (2 folders)
      - Statistics
    - Hall of Fame, Bell's election to, 1950
    - Laboratory notes, 1909 (Box 433)
    - Postage stamp of Bell, 1940
  - Addition II
    - Docket of application for United States patents
      - Vol. 1, 19 Mar.-28 Oct. 1881
      - Vol. 2, 28 Oct. 1881-23 Feb. 1883
      - Vol. 3, 2 Mar. 1883-11 Apr. 1887
      - Vol. 4, 19 Apr. 1887-14 Apr. 1896
      - Vol. 5, 23 Apr. 1896-19 Mar. 1902
      - Vols. 6-7, 25 Mar. 1902-Dec. 1915 (bound together)
      - Vol. 8, 1 Jan. 1916-23 July 1920 (Box 434)
      - Vol. 9, 24 July 1920-14 May 1925
    - Docket of British cases
      - Vol. 1, 19 Feb. 1941-19 May 1945
      - Vol. 2, 19 Feb. 1941-21 Dec. 1948
      - Vol. 3, 24 May-2 Aug. 1945
      - Vol. 4, 24 May 1945-28 Apr. 1954
  - Addition III (Box 435)
    - American Annals of the Deaf
      - 1847-1856, (8 vols.)
      - 1857-1871, (8 vols.) (Box 436)
      - 1872-1879, (8 vols.) (Box 437)
      - 1880-1888, (9 vols.) (Box 438)
      - 1889-1896, (8 vols.) (Box 439)
      - 1897-1902, (6 vols.) (Box 440)
      - 1903-1908, (6 vols.) (Box 441)
      - 1913-1915, (3 vols.) (Box 442)
    - Correspondence (Box 443)
      - Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard, 1891, n.d.
      - Fairchild, Marian ("Daisy"), n.d.
    - Scrapbooks, ca. 1880-1881
  - Addition IV (Box 444)
    - Bell patent litigation, published court proceedings
      - The Bell Patents in the United States Courts, 1880-1893
      - The Telephone Appeals (Box 445)
        - Drawbaugh case
          - Abstract of proofs, n.d.
          - Brief for Bell Co., n.d.
        - General brief for Bell Co., 1886 (Box 446)
        - Oral arguments for Bell Co., 1886
  - Addition V
    - Volta Prize Award Commission, 1879
      - Names of commission members and candidates for the prize
      - Report describing the telephone
      - Resolution recommending Alexander Graham Bell for the prize
- Oversize, 1872-1956, n.d. (Box OV 1-OV 8)
  Oversize material organized and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Family Papers (Box OV 1)
    - Bell, Alexander Melville
      - Family correspondence
        - Bell, Alexander Graham
          - 1872-1873, n.d. (Container 4)
          - 1890 (Container 7)
      - Lecture file (Box OV 2)
        - Advertisements, n.d. (Container 21)
    - Bell, Mabel Gardiner Hubbard (Box OV 3)
      - Family correspondence
        - Bell, Alexander Graham
          - 1895 (Container 44)
  - General Correspondence
    - Alphabetical file
      - Selfridge, Thomas E., 1908 (Container 134)
  - Subject File
    - Aviation
      - Blueprints, n.d. (Container 149)
      - Kites, 1898-1901 (Container 152)
      - The Silver Dart, 1959 (Container 154) (Box OV 4)
    - Bell Museum, Baddeck, Nova Scotia, Canada, 1956 (Container 157)
    - Centenary of Alexander Graham Bell's birth (Box OV 5)
      - Scrapbook, 1947 (Container 172)
    - Deaf (Box OV 6)
      - Charts of deaf families, n.d. (Container 179)
      - Heredity
        - Charts, n.d. (Container 186)
    - Movie, The Story of Alexander Graham Bell (Box OV 7)
      - Scrapbook, 1939 (Container 267)
    - Photophone (Box OV 8)
      - Miscellany, 1879-1880, n.d. (Container 270)
    - Scientific notebooks
      - 1877-1881 (Container 272)
    - Scientific study, "Contracts of Scientific Matter," n.d. (Container 274)
    - Telephone
      - Specifications, 1878 (Container 318)
      - Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1877 (Container 321)
- Microfilm, 1861-1922
  Two microfilm editions of Alexander Graham Bell's home notes and some his laboratory notes produced by the National Geographic Society. The original notebooks are in the Scientific Notebooks series. Also includes a negative microfilm copy of “The Tongue,” a poem written by Alexander Bell (1790-1865).
  - Microfilm I, 1879-1914 (Reel 1-4)
    Laboratory notes filmed in approximate chronological order. A set of volumes, 1880-1893, is filmed out of sequence at the end of the microfilm edition.
    Microfilm shelf no. 10,998.
    - Laboratory notes (Reel 1)
      - Vol. 69, 6 Dec. 1879-5 Jan. 1880
      - Vol. 70, 7-26 Jan. 1880
      - Vol. 71, 27 Jan.-4 Mar. 1880
      - Vol. 73, 4 Mar.-12 May 1880
      - Vol. 74, 14 May-11 June 1880
      - Vols. 2-30, 26 Apr. 1880-13 June 1890 See Reels 3-4
      - Vol. 31, 29 Dec. 1891-5 June 1893
      - Vol. 35, 28 Oct.-28 Dec. 1895
      - Vol. 34, 21 Aug.-25 Oct. 1895
      - Vol. 33, 11 Jan.-21 Aug. 1895
      - Vol. 32, 6 June 1893-10 Jan. 1895
      - Vol. 36, 30 Dec. 1895-3 June 1896
      - Vol. 37, 4 June-24 July 1896
      - Vol. 38, 24 July-7 Sept. 1896
      - Vol. 39A, 7 Sept.-30 Oct. 1896
      - Vol. 39B, 30 Oct.-19 Nov. 1896 (Reel 2)
      - Vol. 40, 20 Nov. 1896-1 July 1897
      - Vol. 41, 1 July-17 Aug. 1897
      - Vol. 42, 4 Aug.-11 Sept. 1897
      - Vol. 43, 18 Aug.-17 Sept. 1897
      - Vol. 44, 14 Sept.-24 Oct. 1897
      - Vol. 45, 25 Oct.-20 Nov. 1897
      - Vol. 48, 22 Aug.-7 Dec. 1899
      - Vol. 47, 10 May-9 Aug. 1899
      - Vol. 49, 6 Aug.-30 Nov. 1901
      - Vol. 50, 8 Aug.-30 Nov. 1901
      - Vol. 51, 9 May-27 Sept. 1902
      - Vol. 52, 28 Sept.-9 Dec. 1902
      - Vol. 53, 16 June-25 Nov. 1903 See Reel 4
      - Vol. 54
        - 12-24 June 1904
        - 12 June-5 Oct. 1904 (Reel 3)
      - Vol. 56, 5 Oct.-22 Dec. 1905
      - Vol. 55, 18-26 Mar. 1905
      - Vol. 59, 10 July 1908-3 Mar. 1909
      - Vol. 60, 14 July-4 Oct. 1911
      - Vol. 61, 5 Oct.-20 Dec. 1911
      - Vol. 64, 21 Nov.-9 Dec. 1912
      - Vol. 62, 9 July-10 Sept. 1912
      - Vol. 63, 11 Sept.-20 Nov. 1912
      - Vol. 65, 3 July-12 Nov. 1913
      - Vol. 66, 13 Nov. 1913-20 July 1914
      - Vol. 67, 21 July-30 Oct. 1914
      - Vol. 68, 31 Oct.-1 Dec. 1914
      - Vol. 2, 26 Apr.-12 May 1880
      - Vol. 3, 12-19 May 1880
      - Vol. 4, 20 May-1 June 1880
      - Vol. 5, 2-10 June 1880
      - Vol. 6, 10-15 June 1880
      - Vol. 7, 16 June-10 July 1880 (Reel 4)
      - Vol. 8, 13-23 July 1880
      - Vol. 9, 23 July-17 Aug. 1880
      - Vol. 10, 20 Aug. 1880-3 June 1881
      - Vol. 11, 4-24 Jan. 1881
      - Vol. 12, 24 Jan.-19 Feb. 1881
      - Vol. 72, 19 Feb.-28 Mar. 1881
      - Vol. 13, 29 Mar.-12 June 1881
      - Vol. 20, 29 July 1882-4 May 1886
      - Vol. 53, 16 June-25 Nov. 1903
      - Vol. 15, 25 June-29 July 1881
      - Vol. 16, 29 July 1881-1 Jan. 1882
      - Vol. 17, 8 Jan.-1 Aug. 1882
      - Vol. 75, 26 Mar.-22 Aug. 1883
      - Vol. 21, 6 Dec. 1883-27 Mar. 1884
      - Vol. 23, 28 Nov. 1885-19 Oct. 1887
      - Vol. 29, 3 Feb.-13 June 1890
      - Vol. 30, 9 Feb. 1890
  - Microfilm II, 1879-1922 (Reel 1-18)
    Home notes and laboratory notes grouped by type of material and filmed chronologically thereunder.
    Microfilm shelf no. 13,638.
    - Home notes, 6 Dec. 1879-18 Jan. 1895 (Reel 1)
    - Laboratory notes, 7 Dec. 1879-2 Nov. 1880 (Reel 2, Reel 1a)
    - Home notes, 18 Jan. 1895-1 Oct. 1896 (Reel 3, Reel 2)
    - Laboratory notes, 7 Sept. 1896-30 Oct. 1896
    - Home notes, 1 Oct. 1896-16 Dec. 1900
    - Laboratory notes, 2 Nov. 1880-10 Jan. 1895 (Reel 4, Reel 2a)
    - Home notes, 16 Dec. 1900-30 June 1903 (Reel 5, Reel 3)
    - Laboratory notes, 11 Jan. 1895-17 Sept. 1897 (Reel 6, Reel 3a)
    - Home notes, 1 July 1903-5 Aug. 1907 (Reel 7, Reel 4)
    - Laboratory notes, 14 Sept. 1897-6 Feb. 1909 (Reel 8, Reel 4a)
    - Home notes, 5 Aug. 1907-5 Oct. 1909 (Reel 9, Reel 5)
    - Laboratory notes, 18 Mar. 1909-15 July 1911 (Reel 10, Reel 5a)
    - Home notes (Reel 11, Reel 6)
      - 6 Oct. 1909-17 Oct. 1912
      - 17 Oct. 1912-18 Mar. 1914 (Reel 12, Reel 7)
      - 18 Mar. 1914-10 Aug. 1915 (Reel 13, Reel 8)
      - 10 Aug. 1915-9 Jan. 1917 (Reel 14, Reel 9)
      - 9 Jan. 1917-21 Mar. 1918 (Reel 15, Reel 10)
      - 21 Mar. 1918-22 Jan. 1920 (Reel 16, Reel 11)
      - 22 Jan. 1920-10 Jan. 1921 (Reel 17, Reel 12)
      - 11 Jan. 1921-23 Nov. 1922 (Reel 18, Reel 13)
  - Microfilm III, 1861 (Reel 1)
    Negative microfilm copy of “The Tongue,” a poem written by Alexander Bell (1790-1865).
    Microfilm shelf no. 16,395. Available through the Library's Photoduplication Service.
    - Bell, Alexander (1790-1865) (Reel 1)
      - Poetry file
        - “The Tongue,” 1861 See also Container 2, same heading